Hello everyone and welcome back to English
Pod, my name is Marco and my name is
Catherine so Marco today we're
talking about rent and housing right we're
actually gonna be moving we're gonna
be going to a new apartment or a new
house and so we're gonna look at
all the words related to this because
sometimes it can be a real hassle
right it can be really difficult absolutely
well you love moving right you were
telling me how much you love moving your
stuff negotiating a new lease well I
like the negotiation of the lease but not
the moving aspect I think I don't
think anyone likes actually I do like it
at times because then you can just
throw away so many things that you have no
need for and you wouldn't throw away
unless you move so let's go check out
today's dialogue to find out
what happens to the characters
okay that's fine bye what happened
that's it I lease is up I have to move what
why can't you renew it the owner
apparently is selling this place to make
way for the construction of a parking
lot well I can help you pack we should
start looking for a new place for you
ASAP I think I might move in with my
parents for a couple of months until I
can find something you know how hard it
is to find a decent place around here
I'm going to have to put most of my stuff
and storage for a while well let me
know if there's anything I can do to help
out actually would you mind looking
after my pet tarantula snake for a
couple of weeks sure
all right we're back so well it's not
much of a big deal I guess if you have
your parents nearby you can just
move back in with your parents easier said
than then true true we'll get to that
in a little bit but let's take a look at
the words that are used today in language
takeaway language takeaway all right so
this first one is an important one
because generally when you're looking for a
house or an apartment there are two things
you can do you can buy a house or you
can lease a house or apartment so lease
here Marco it's basically to rent right
it's a contract where you agree to
pay a monthly or a or a quarterly fee for
using that house or apartment so do you
own your apartment or do you lease it no
outline I lease yeah I'm not a home owner
yet right so owning a home is a lot more
expensive at one kind of period where
you have to just pay in and maybe a
mortgage but leasing is just a monthly
fee like you said so in this case they
had to leave because their lease was
expired exactly so you can at the end of
a lease do one of two things you can
stop and you can find a new apartment or
you can renew your lease all right and
that's our next word to renew your lease
basically means to to continue to
continue and this is actually a good word
because it can be used with a con
any contract because really a lease is a
kind of contract and so I can say I renewed
my job contract or maybe a magazine
subscription yeah you renewed your
magazine subscription it's a it's a way of
saying that you've committed to paying
for the next six months or one year okay
well and after that the as we said
the person decided to move in with the
parents so move in move in well we
can say he moved his car he put it in a
different place but to move in is
actually to to change houses or the change
apartments and you you're literally
moving your things and you're moving your
clothes and you're moving into a new
home so you're living a new place so in
this case this person is going to live
with the parents move in all right and
our next word is when you have to move
you have to pack okay so you can pack a
lot of things in this case you're packing
a box with all of your belongings your
books and your pillows and all that but you
can also pack a suitcase or you can pack
luggage so packing is putting things
into something so that you can move them
so you can carry them or take them somewhere
exactly so in this case you have to
pack your things put them in boxes to
take them to your new home and our last
word is an acronym when you said ASAP
all right snap snap come on ASAP mark
ASAP describe this for us quickly all
right so ASAP is an acronym for as soon
as possible okay so you often see
this in the office on envelopes or emails
right so please respond ASAP ASAP this
means please respond right away as soon
as you can as soon as possible all
right so five great words that we've just
taken a look at let's listen to our
dialogue again and we'll be right back
okay that's fine bye what happened
that's it I lease is up I have to move what
why can't you renew it the owner apparently
is selling this place to make way
for the construction of a parking lot
well I can help you pack we should start
looking for a new place for you ASAP I
think I might move in with my parents for a
couple of months until I can find
something you know how hard it is to find a
decent place around here I'm gonna have
to put most of my stuff in storage for a
while well let me know if there's
anything I can do to help out actually what
do you mind looking after my pet
torrential and snake for a couple of weeks
sure all right we're back and we have
a couple of different phrases for you
so let's look at those
now influencey builder
fluency builder
my first one's a little
bit unusual we heard the phrase my
lease is up so Mark let's talk about this
phrase to be up all right so if something
is up as in this case the lease it
means it's expired it's finished right
so it's over it's up you can also say
our time is up right if we have a meeting
so that's all the time I have time to
go away time is up very good so
it's always related to time or maybe a
contract is in this case and my or
your lease is up so it means over or
finished all right so moving on to our
second phrase to make way for all right
so this is a great one this often makes
me think of kings and queens in the
old days is a make way for the king so
you have to get out of the way yeah get
out of the way or to clear some space
for them to move because there's too
much stuff in the way and so in this
case the owner of the apartment with the
guy was living in is trying to make
some space or make way for a parking lot
right so he's basically going to sell
the building or house and build a parking
lot instead so they are making way
for the new parking lot they're clearing
space and this is actually really
sad because my childhood home they
destroyed to make way for a larger
ugly building house yeah it happens all
the time now they're making way for
malls and in the big buildings and all
the little houses are destroyed and
well moving on to our last phrase the
the person asked the friend if he
would mind looking after the pet snake
enter Angela I would mind you don't
like snakes I don't like I don't live with
them so would you mind how this is a
nice way to start a sentence if you want
to ask for a favor right exactly so
here's an here's an alternative hey Marco
can you do this for me I could maybe I
could say Marco would you mind doing
this for me it sounds it's more polite
it is more polite and it's a little bit
gentler mm-hmm yeah so it's nice
it's a nice way of asking someone for a
favor exactly and that's why this is
funny because the favor is not like would
you mind watching my kitty the favor is
would you mind watching my poisonous pets
all right all right so would you mind it
but in the end the person agreed so it's
it works right it does work so would
you mind so listeners would you mind
listening to today's dialogue one more
time at its normal speed before we come
back to you and talk more
about renting an apartment
okay that's fine bye what happened
that's it I laces up I have to move what
why can't you renew it the owner
apparently is selling this place to make
way for the construction of a parking
lot well I can help you pack we should
start looking for a new place for you
ASAP I think I might move in with my
parents for a couple of months until I
can find something you know how hard it
is to find a decent place around here
I'm gonna have to put most of my stuff
and storage for a while well let me
know if there's anything I can do to help
out actually would you
mind looking after my pet
torrential and snake for
a couple of weeks sure
all right so moving in now you have
different stages in your life right when you
move out for example you move out of
your parents home and you live on your own
and then maybe like in this case you
would move back in with your parents how do
you see that happening I see it very
often my brother just moved back in with my
parents really yeah I think that it
depends on the person honestly I mean
especially because the economy has really
been suffering for the last year a lot
people are doing this because you
know in a lot of cities in America you can
spend a thousand to two thousand dollars
a month for an apartment to rent and
that's a small apartment or a shared
apartment and so I understand this is a
really well it's a better option now
than it was before because everyone
wants independence right sometimes
you just can't afford it exactly and it's a
cultural thing because some people
move out of their parents home maybe for
college it's very common in the US
for a study in another city or another
state right and but then maybe coming
back home and moving in with your
parents or another cultures maybe
they don't move out at all maybe they only
move out once they're married exactly
so a lot of people in China I think in
Shanghai specifically don't move out
until don't move out of their parents home
until they're going to get married
right but it does make sense and in many
big metropolis because as you say
rent is expensive living on your own is
expensive and well you don't have
anyone to share those costs with like gas
water electricity even food right
it's definitely more people and that's
to mention a little bit scary living
on your own for the first time it is a
little bit scary what about having somebody
move in with you maybe a roommate or
girlfriend boyfriend that's always a
big step you know big commitment and
you're in a relationship and you ask
your partner to move in with you so yeah
the step before marriage I guess
there's not there's nothing before that
nothing before marriage no that's
pretty much it you tell me I don't know all
right that's all the time we have for
today but be sure to come to our website
englishpud.com if you have any questions
or any comments about this topic we
would be glad to have your input on it
and we'll see you guys there and if you
have any suggestions for the step before
the step before marriage please let us
know because we're in the dark on
this one so until next time right bye
right!